Guide to the Duke Family papers on the Duke Farms residence, 1859-2004 and undated RL.01437
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Duke Family papers on the Duke Farms residence
1859-2004
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Duke family
RL.01437
341 Linear Feet
Duke Farms, a 2,700 acre estate located in Hillsborough, New Jersey, was developed by James Buchanan (J.B.) Duke beginning in 1893. After J.B. Duke's death in 1925, Doris Duke inherited the property. Over the course of nearly seven decades she worked to continue the legacy of Duke Farms and introduced environmentally-friendly and innovative farming methods into the operations of Duke Farms and purchased and restored farms and farmstead structures in order to forestall the rapid loss of farmland to urban development. When she died she left the majority of her estate to the Doris Duke Charitable Foundation with her expressed wish that Duke Farms be used to drive positive change on a number of key issues regarding the stewardship of the natural environment. The collection is arranged into four series: Administrative Records, Duke Business Office Records, Duke Farms Main Residence Records, and Architectural Records. It spans the years 1859 to 2004, beginning with the early vision and evolution of the estate by James Buchanan (J.B.) Duke, the enhancement and management of the estate by Doris Duke after she inherited control of it upon her father's death, and ending with the general upkeep of the estate after Doris Duke's death in 1993. The collection primarily documents the daily operations of running, renovating, and maintaining the Duke Farms estate, and includes daily activity reports, correspondence, notes, and specifications for various architectural projects at Duke Farms, invoices and vouchers for repairs at different buildings on the estate, cattle inventories and cow registrations, financial ledgers and cashbooks, and security ledgers and reports. The architectural records are further arranged into seven sub series and contain a wide assortment of records, including blueprints, diazo prints, site plans, schedules, and maps. The materials document a variety of design, construction, and farm-related activities at Duke Farms.
41,880 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research, however there are restrictions on certain materials within the collection. See Series level descriptions for more information.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use. Due to the fragility of the Architectural records, The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Digital use copies in this collection have been migrated to a library server and can only be accessed onsite in the Rubenstein Library Reading Room. To request access please contact Research Services prior to visiting the library.
Provenance
The Duke Family papers on the Duke Farms residence were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a donation from the Doris Duke Charitable Foundation in June 2009.
Historical Note
Duke Farms, a 2,700 acre estate located in Hillsborough, New Jersey, was developed by James Buchanan (J.B.) Duke beginning in 1893 when he purchased 327 acres of the John V. Veghte farm. Over the next 12 years J.B. Duke purchased 40 additional parcels of farmland to create a 2,000 acre estate which would eventually be named Duke Farms. Duke's plan was to create seemingly natural vistas out of the flat farmland and include lakes, fountains, roads, and statuary throughout the estate. The majority of the landscaping of Duke Farms took place between 1899 and 1911, with the primary focus being the creation of a park open and free to the public at all times of the year. During this time, he also focused on the construction of agricultural buildings rather than his personal residence, and retained the architectural firm Kendall, Taylor & Stevens to design infrastructure and buildings such as the Coach Barn devoted to agriculture and horticultural production. In 1915, Duke Farms was officially closed to the public and the estate was transformed from a park to farm land to help the war effort.
After J.B. Duke's death in 1925, Doris Duke inherited the property. Over the course of nearly seven decades she worked to continue the legacy of Duke Farms by cultivating the land to produce food crops, raising Jersey cattle, sheep, and pigs, and growing a variety of flowers serving both household needs and the commercial market. She also introduced environmentally-friendly and innovative farming methods into the operations of Duke Farms and purchased and restored farms and farmstead structures in order to forestall the rapid loss of farmland to urban development. When she died she left the majority of her estate to the Doris Duke Charitable Foundation with her expressed wish that Duke Farms be used to drive positive change on a number of key issues regarding the stewardship of the natural environment.
Collection Overview
The Duke Family papers on the Duke Farms residence (formerly DF.3) is part of the Doris Duke Charitable Foundation Historical Archives which were donated to the Duke University. David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library by the Doris Duke Charitable Foundation. The collection is arranged into four series: Administrative Records, Duke Business Office Records, Duke Farms Main Residence Records, and Architectural Records. It spans the years 1859 to 2004, beginning with the early vision and evolution of the estate by James Buchanan (J.B.) Duke, the enhancement and management of the estate by Doris Duke after she inherited control of it upon her father's death, and ending with the general upkeep of the estate after Doris Duke's death in 1993. The collection primarily documents the daily operations of running, renovating, and maintaining the Duke Farms estate, and includes deeds, mortgages, and agreements relating to the formation of J.B. Duke's Hillsborough property, daily activity reports, correspondence, notes, and specifications for various architectural projects at Duke Farms, invoices and vouchers for repairs at different buildings on the estate including the Main Residence, cattle inventories and cow registrations, financial ledgers and cashbooks, and security ledgers and reports. The architectural records are further arranged into seven sub series and contain a wide assortment of records, including blueprints, diazo prints, site plans, schedules, and maps. The materials document a variety of design, construction, and farm-related activities at Duke Farms. The arrangement of the collection varies with each series.
Related Material
Duke Family New York Apartments Collection, 1908-1997
Duke University Archives/David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Doris Duke Papers on the Falcon Lair Residence, 1937-1999
Duke University Archives/David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Doris Duke Papers on the Shangri La Residence, 1932-2003
Duke University Archives/David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Doris Duke Papers on the Rough Point Residence, 1922-1997
Duke University Archives/David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Architectural drawing -- United States -- 20th century; Duke family; Farm Management; Hillsborough (N.J.); Architecture -- Designs and plans; Duke, James Buchanan, 1856-1925; Duke, Doris; Duke family
- Administrative Records, 1859-2004 and undated
  Scope and Contents note
  Topics in this series are widely varied, however they are all related to the daily operations of the Duke Farms estate. The materials begin with J.B. Duke, primarily documenting the early evolution of the estate from a "gentleman's" farm (raising and breeding cattle and horse) to a public park, and finally to a large-scale agricultural production farm to support the war effort. Materials include the original deeds, mortgages, and agreements relating to the formation of J.B. Duke's Hillsborough property, the certificate of incorporation of the Duke's Farm Company in 1917, correspondence and invoices for purchases of equipment and Jersey cows for the farm, lists of plants and flowers sold, analysis of profit and loss accounts, daily activity reports, and correspondence, notes, and specifications for various architectural projects at Duke Farms, including the construction of a "country house" and the greenhouses. Of particular interest are the letterbooks, which range from 1916 to 1927. The letters detail the daily operations of Duke's Farms, including the purchases of plants, trees, and flowers for the estate, rent paid, farm equipment requests, and letters to Horace Trumbauer regarding the construction of two cottages on the estate.
  The series continues with Doris Duke, beginning with her inheritance of the property after J.B. Duke's death in 1925 and ending in 2004 with materials related to the handling of the Estate of Doris Duke after her death in 1993. The materials document the broad, diverse daily activities of the estate, including leases, memoranda and correspondence related to land, houses, and field crops, invoices and vouchers for repairs at different buildings on the estate, and financial statements, receipts, and disbursements related to the daily operations. The materials also document Doris Duke's interests in conservation, raising Jersey cattle, and organic farming, and include memoranda concerning agricultural conservation programs at Duke Farms, invoices and vouchers relating to soil and water conservation, cattle inventories and cow registrations, and proposals for organic farming at Duke Farms. Of particular interest are letters from Hillsborough residents who supported Doris Duke in her land preservation efforts.
  At least half of the materials are in oversize boxes and primarily consist of ledgers, financial journals, cashbooks, voucher records, and inventories. The materials in this series are arranged loosely in chronological order.
  Conditions Governing Access note
  RESTRICTED: Access to several folders in boxes 23, 35, 45, 246, 247, 249, and 253 are restricted and require prior written approval from the Doris Duke Charitable Foundation to view.
  - Letter to Duke’s Farm from Lord & Burnham Co. discussing “revised arrangements of plant tables in Summer House and Piazza.” 1900 (Tracing paper drawing moved to Architectural Drawings Collection) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence relating to J.B. Duke’s Agreement with Raritan Water Company and Public Service Corp. of N.J. and Somerset, Union, and Middlesex Lighting Co. for electrical current. 1906 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Letter to Agnes H. McWilliams, Secretary & Cashier at Duke’s Farm from The Darling Pump & Mfg. Co., Ltd. relating to hub end gate values and the possibility of doing work with Duke Farms. April 12, 1909 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Letter to Agnes H. McWilliams from M. Smith relating to a bill from J.B. Duke’s water rent amounting to $1,020 from Raritan Water Power Co. July 24, 1909 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence from Horace Trumbauer (signed) to D.J. Smith at Duke Farms referencing Sax and Abbott Construction Co.’s proposed design of the Pump and Filter House at Duke Farms. 1909 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence relating to American Water Softener Co. and Belmont Iron Works’s work at Duke Farms. Some letters reference the installation of structural steel work at the Pump House. 1909 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Letter to J.B. Duke from A.N. Randolph, electrical contractor, stating his proposal to install electrical light fixtures at several locations on Duke Farms. June 21, 1910 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Letter to Mrs. Louise Elmendorf outlining terms of conditions for sale of her property to J.B. Duke. September 29, 1910 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence relating to plans and specifications for the Country House (Old Foundation). Letters discuss cut limestone and concord granite work as well as the erection of the proposed terrace walls. Letters are addressed to Horace Trumbauer, architect, and D.J. Smith, Superintendent at Duke Farms. File also includes “Specifications for Cut Stone of Terraces of Country House.” 1910–1911 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Letter to D.J. Smith from D.J. Shaffer relating to the Gasolene Engine Generator set for house lighting in J.B. Duke’s residence and a test of this set by D.J. Shaffer, Chief Engineer at Duke Farms. January 21, 1915 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence and notes relating to insurance coverage for the greenhouses and the Florists’ Hale Association of America By-laws. 1915 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence relating to business matters at Duke Farms Company. 1916–1917 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Letter to D.J. Smith, General Manager, Duke Farms Co., from J.A. Casey of U.S. Railroad Administration, referring “to matter of proposed elevator construction on the Duke Estate.” December 19, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence and related materials concerning the Raritan Water Power Company. Includes a copy of the act to incorporate RWPC (1863). 1936–1956 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence relating to daily operations at Duke Farms. Topics include shipments between estates, Doris Duke’s sale of the new Power House to the Supreme Fur Dressing Company, Inc., conservation of paintings from 1 E. 78th St., the removal of Mr. Cromwell’s furniture, and the lighting installations by Rudolph Wendel. 1938–1943 (Note includes invoices from Ruby Ross Wood) (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, memoranda, and related materials concerning the Raritan Water Power Company. Includes Easements, like the SRVSA Deed (December 3, 1957). 1943–1960 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence relating to daily operations at Duke Farms. Topics include Jersey cattle, orchids, maintenance of the Japanese Garden near the Main Residence, the transfer of silver to the Guaranty Trust Co. (1945), and Treasury Department forms. 1944–1947 (1 of 2) (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence relating to daily operations at Duke Farms. Topics include Jersey cattle, orchids, maintenance of the Japanese Garden near the Main Residence, the transfer of silver to the Guaranty Trust Co. (1945), and Treasury Department forms. 1944–1947 (2 of 2) (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence and notes relating to daily operations at Duke Farms. Topics include shipments between estates, broken bronzes loaned to The Asian Institute (1948), appraisal of furniture at Duke Farms (1948), and investigative services. 1948–1957 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence from local realtors, interested in purchasing land at Duke Farms (land was not for sale). 1955–1963 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence relating to a condo property located near railroad tracks (most likely on the border of Duke Farms). 1957 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence relating to daily business matters at Duke Farms. Topics include lawsuits with florists for their payments for flowers purchased from Duke Farms, the weakening of the Raritan dam, the erection of the public service high tower transmission line on or near Duke Farms, and a tax Assessment on the new greenhouse. Includes lawsuit of Doris Duke v. L. Greene (1962). 1958–1963 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence relating to a request from Tectonic Associates, a company neighboring Duke Farms, to clean out ditch on Duke Farms property which impeded storm drainage on their property. 1959 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, memoranda, and related materials concerning Easements on Duke Farms (utility Easements). 1962–1972 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence relating to routine business matters at Duke Farms. 1964–1969 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence and memoranda relating to daily administrative tasks at Duke Farms. Tasks are mostly maintenance related. 1965–1986 (1 of 2) (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence and memoranda relating to daily administrative tasks at Duke Farms. Tasks are mostly maintenance related. 1965–1986 (2 of 2) (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Administrative records, routine. 1966–1990 (bulk dates 1987–1988) (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence and memoranda relating to the possibility of donating some land to a college site in N.J. 1967 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence sent to Doris Duke regarding work done on Duke Farms and the Raritan Canal. July 8, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Memoranda relating to inquiries into Doris Duke’s donation of 51.597 acres to the U.S.A. (Veterans Administration). 1968–1979 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence and memoranda relating to daily administrative matters including issues with The Central Railroad Co. of N.J. 1969–1970 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Memoranda and printed materials regarding cleaning rugs and other items at Duke Farms. 1970, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Memoranda and related research articles concerning food and water contamination. 1971 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence and memoranda relating to the closing of Duke’s Parkway. The Hillsborough Township Committee discussed the possibility of creating a new County Road. 1973–1974 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence and related materials concerning Doris Duke’s license of a Heliport at Duke Farms. 1970–1976 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Memoranda and related materials concerning agricultural conservation programs at Duke Farms. 1975 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence and memoranda relating to daily administrative tasks at Duke Farms (Transferred to Archives from P. Lerch July 6, 2004). 1975–1981 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence and memoranda relating to Lease between Duke Farms and Ever Lea Farms for farmland (Duchess and Davis). 1975–1984 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence relating to various housing and property Leases between Doris Duke and lessees. 1976–1978 (1 of 2) (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence relating to various housing and property Leases between Doris Duke and lessees. 1976–1978 (2 of 2) (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence and memoranda relating to J. Preston Quick’s lease of farmland at Duke Farms. 1977–1989 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, memoranda, and related materials concerning deer feeding and humane deterrents at Duke Farms. 1978, 1980–1981 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Memoranda relating to updates and work assignments of V. Clemens to Doris Duke, re farm. 1979–1980 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence relating to a variety of issues concerning the rental of House No. 120. Issues include electricity usage and arson of barn and chicken coop. 1979–1981 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Memoranda relating to status and condition of House No. 49. 1979, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence and memoranda relating to James Norz’s lease of Field Nos. 1, 2, 33, 37, and 30. 1979–1983 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Memoranda relating to employees’ purchases of firewood. 1979–1982, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence and related maps and other materials concerning the widening of Route 206. 1979–1986 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence and memoranda relating to maintenance of houses leased to employees. Includes copies of blank Leases. 1979–1987 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, memoranda and related materials concerning the widening of Route 206 and its impact on Duke Farms. Also includes newspaper clippings. 1979–1988 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence relating to the amount of electricity used at House No. 59, rented by Matthew Leo. 1980–1981 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Memoranda relating to the Lease of House No. 75. Includes photos. 1980–1981 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence and memoranda relating to maintenance and repairs at House No. 52. 1981–1984 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence and memoranda relating to various housing rentals at Duke Farms. 1981–1986 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, memoranda and related materials concerning the leasing of House No. 52A. Lessees were Rev. Greer S. Imbrie and his Wife, Rosaline L. Roche. File includes copies of Leases. 1981–1987 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Memoranda relating to Ron David’s leasing of the Kaufman Farm. 1982–1984 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Memoranda and related materials concerning the demolition of the bridge near the North Gate. 1985 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Memoranda relating to personnel benefits, policies, and procedures. 1985 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Memoranda relating to understanding by all employees that lease homes at Duke Farms with Doris Duke. 1985–1986 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence relating to outside inquiries into the purchase of land at Duke Farms. Doris Duke not interested. 1986 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Notes relating to trees on property, landscape architecture, and research. 1986–1987 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence relating to Doris Duke and the Cook College initiative. 1987–1992 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Memoranda relating to daily administrative matters at Duke Farms. 1988 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence and memoranda relating to Frederick Brigg’s Lease at Prescott Farm, Rhode Island. 1988–1989 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Memoranda relating to daily administrative tasks including miscellaneous appliances. 1989 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Memoranda relating to administrative matters including purchase order approvals, work and equipment needs as well as some personal business like clothing purchases. Memos maintained by DBO staff. 1989–1990 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence relating to the re-numbering of several houses at River Road and Duke’s Parkway. 1990 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence relating to mostly administrative matters at Duke Farms. File includes miscellaneous papers originally classified as ‘Miscellaneous’ in original file. 1990–1994 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Memoranda from DBO accounting for completed purchase orders (including clothing purchased for Doris Duke). File includes other correspondence relating to purchases of vacuum cleaners, tuning of pianos at Duke Farms, and employees’ housing at Duke Farms. 1991 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Memoranda from DBO relating to purchases for Duke Farms. (includes some personal purchases for Doris Duke). 1991 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Memorandum regarding nursery stock transplants at Duke Farms. Includes the spraying and fertilizing program schedule at Duke Farms. 1991–1992 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - FAX cover sheets, daily administrative matters. 1992 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Stationary, Duke Business Office and Patrick Lerch, Executive Director, Duke Farms Foundation. Circa 1993–2004 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence relating to the rental of several houses at Duke Farms by Turpin Real Estate, N.J. 1995–1996 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Memoranda, invoices and related materials concerning the health and status of Paula Cottontail, rabbit. 1995–1996 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Nomination Form for the National Registration of Historical Places, undated (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Invoice for painting of Stables at Coach Barn. 1894 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Itemized statements for Duke’s Farm & Stables (Company). 1894 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Invoice to Raritan Water Co., Inc. from Geo. Focht Sons, Iron Works. 1905 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Invoices for J.B. Duke’s purchases of statues for the grounds at Duke Farms. 1905–1906 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Invoices and related materials concerning work on bridges, canals, and dams, mainly by Richards & Gaston, Inc. 1905–1916 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - List of machinery at Old Power House, list of machinery purchased from Raritan Water Power Co. and handwritten list of various purchases relating to the Pump and Filter House. 1909 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Invoice, Knox Fence Co., purchased by Louis Gaston. 1911 (Box 6, Folder 15)